[Applause]
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
SC radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
or / software this is Stefan silikov for
software engineering radio my guest
today is von Vernon who is a consultant
mentor and author best known for his
contributions under the main driven
design community Vaughn has more than 25
years of experience in software design
development and architecture he's
written a book on DDD called
implementing domain driven design and
teaches a course based on that material
all over the world in this episode we
talk about the topic of his most recent
book reactive messaging patterns with
the act remodel Sivan thank you very
much for being with us today let's dive
right in and talk a bit about reactive
programming
what does reactive programming mean and
is it something new or something that
we've been doing for a long time well
it's it's both new and old and I'll
explain why I say that reactive
programming let's say on the server side
is being you know going through
repopulation now or becoming popular on
the client side however or in the UI you
could say that reactive programming has
been going on for a long time but just
to give you some history as far back as
1973 Carl Hewitt was working on this
experimental model called actor model
and although the computing power and so
forth that was available at the time
wasn't really
for parallel or concurrent processing
Carl Hewitt still formulated this this
model to computation way back then in
1973 if we move forward to the mid to
say late 1980s early 1990s a lot of
people a lot of developers started
working with GUI programming whether it
was on the windows API or using x
windows or something like that they were
using reactive programming even though
it probably wasn't called reactive at
the time I mean I I don't remember that
it was it was just GUI programming what
I was doing at the time and so the idea
though is that as a user would move the
mouse or click some command button or
type some information some characters
into a field the UI behind the scenes
was reacting to this because there were
constant events flowing as the user
moved the mouse or clicked the mouse or
clicked a button or typed this caused
various events to be created and and
sent to the program and the program
would react to those so you could say
that a lot of people have done reactive
programming especially if you think in
terms of let's say doing web development
today if you've ever written any sort of
JavaScript that reacts to the UI that
you're presenting to the user in a
browser and you react to some sort of
mouse movement or button click or
something like that then there is
reactive programming happening there
mm-hmm
in terms of reactive on the server side
this is something that
is being popularized now and and
something that's a bit different and so
you can imagine using the same basic
principles same concepts but we're
components on the server side are
reacting to some sort of stimulus rather
than just the UI okay so some explain to
us how the actor model actually works
okay so actor model focuses on an actor
as the central and primary unit of
computation this means that an actor is
like you know you might think of an
actor as this this cell or a single
responsibility kind of computational
unit that's responsible for one thing
and one thing specifically and it knows
how to handle or react to some set of
incoming messages so it reacts to some
sort of stimulus and as a reaction to
that stimulus it may change its internal
state it may send a message back to the
sender of the message that it is
currently handling or it may send out
messages to other actors as outgoing
messages all at the same time the actor
does not have to be concerned about the
typical concurrency problems that are
faced by various other kinds of you know
a different style of computing where
we're using multi-threading across any
number of components because the actor
is receiving the message asynchronously
and it's receiving the messages one at a
time
so it never has to worry about two
threads working through its state at the
same time there will only be one thread
assigned to the actor at any given time
so this means that the actor must also
share nothing about its internal state
it it must just keep all of its internal
state to itself and thus because of that
as it is handling one message at a time
that message handler can operate on
across the entire state of the actor and
not have to worry about race conditions
in any way so that's you know primarily
how the actor works you could also think
of the actor as being kind of a perfect
transactional boundary that everything
that happens within the actor as it's
dealing with one message at a time is a
perfect boundary for transactional
control and no other actors outside of
that actor will be influenced directly
by what happens to the state of the
actor at that time so it's a it's a
great transactional boundary as well so
it sounds a bit like like sort of an an
active active object of some kind it has
some properties of objects but it also
has a threat of Patrol yes exactly
that's a good good way to put it think
of think of an actor as being an object
and you you might think of an object
that has methods on it and public
methods can be invoked by other objects
well it's it's similar with actor except
that when you send an actor a message it
doesn't immediately invoke a method on
the actor the message is received
asynchronously from the message send
itself so the message will be handled
let's say on a different thread
inside the actor so so there is that
asynchronous and concurrency going on
with the actor but inside the actor as
its dealing with that it could call its
own method internally so yeah it is sort
of like objects with asynchronous
messaging so how many actors with a
typical system have would it be a lot or
is it as many as threads what's the
approach there yeah so it really depends
on the application if you were to look
at a typical actor model toolkit or
library they're typically able to manage
millions of actors if that's as many as
the system needs it's really a matter of
how much memory is available and of
course how many threads can be run by
the processor at any given time but you
know depending on on what your
application actually needs
you could have dozens of actors or
hundreds of actors or thousands or tens
of thousands of actors but you could
even scale as as many as millions of
actors at one time within a single note
each of the actors is scheduled to run
it doesn't own a threat of its own
typically the way that you would design
an actor model library is by having a
pool of threads that are available to be
used by the actors and as and then
there's an internal scheduler that knows
that that a given actor has messages
that need to be processed and so the
scheduler will give the actors that have
messages to process
a thread for some number of messages and
so the the computing is spread across
the various actors through this
scheduler mm-hmm so what's the relation
of the actual model to Scala and akka
okay so actor model again was first
worked on back in 1973 and if you were
to look at the use of actor model from
that time forward it was actually I
would say you you would have to admit
that it was quite limited and used
primarily because there weren't a lot of
cores on individual machines it was more
about scaling up than scaling out if you
if you were to take a leap forward from
a Carl Hewitt stay until actor model was
more widely in use you'd have to go to
look at the Erlang programming language
and actors are supported in Erlang now
Erlang has become a more popular
language of late but I still would say
that it's not really a completely
mainstream language like Java or C sharp
has become but if you look at Scala
if you know enough about Erlang and then
take a look at Scala and akka you can
see a lot of similarities between the
Scala programming language with akka and
Erlang so you know if you kind of
thought of using it maybe a little bit
like an Erlang flavored language with
actors on the JVM that's kind of what
Scala and akka give you although I would
say that you can also get a real sense
of of Java's influence on on scala as
well so it's not just like programming
in early so how would you how would you
compare
the actual effects of those approaches
so I'm not talking about the theory but
the actual a programming experience when
you've any program using the actual
model or program using a a thread based
model explicitly or maybe using I don't
know async i/o in an invented fashion
what's the what's the what's the
downsides and what is the what is the
was the benefits of each model or
particularly what is the benefit of the
acro model right so if you look at just
object-oriented programming you have an
object you can invoke a method on an
object now in the in the smoke and the
small talk programming language believe
it or not a small talk you know is a
language that is based on message
sending so if you think about a method
invocation on an object that's that's
more of like a modern way for us to talk
about it because that's actually how it
works with Java or with c-sharp but with
the small talk language when I have an
object I literally send it a message the
method that gets invoked on that actual
object is a mapping of a message send to
a method selector that's internal to the
object and even though by default small
talk was a model that was not concurrent
but you know basically each message sent
to an object was handled on the same
thread as the invocation or the the
message send still there was this idea
of a separation between the external
object that was sent a message and the
internal object that received the
message as a method invocation so kind
of if you think about it in that way it
helps us to take
one step forward toward actor model or
even concurrent programming now if you
just think about that same small talk
application where I send a message to an
object and that object is when it
receives that message send then it's
going to map to an internal method think
of that point where the message gets
sent as now happening asynchronously so
as soon as the message is sent there's a
queue somewhere that receives the
invocation request but the invocation
won't actually occur until that object
has an opportunity to accept the latest
message and react to it so that that's
sort of a you know a stepwise refinement
to getting toward actor model on the
other hand if you think about
multi-threaded programming in general
and the kinds of programming api's that
are available to us let's say just with
the java programming language we have
the a concept of a thread and basically
it's our responsibility as programmers
to create a thread to start the thread
running to somehow receiving input to
that thread how do we how do we receive
input that's up to the discretion of the
application designer or the or the tool
designer that's working on this this
concurrency approach to programming so
there's there needs to be some way for
that thread to receive some sort of
input but let's say that we're running
our thread on a loop and whenever we
don't have any work to do we we decide
to sleep and whenever we do have some
work to do we allow that work to be done
and then we go back into a
and weight mode until we have you know
some more input to process and because
there is no way to you know
automatically prevent that thread from
receiving input from multiple threads at
one time we have to be worried about
synchronization so do we do we have you
know full rights to the data that that
thread has within its object its its
some object state at any given time or
is it possible for that thread to
receive multiple input requests
simultaneously and therefore we have to
get into things like you know do we
synchronize this method or do we
synchronize this hot block of code
within a method how do we synchronize it
how do we make sure that we don't turn
our multi-threaded program back into a
glorified single-threaded program
because we are just so poor at writing
multi-threaded code that that's what we
end up doing is just blocking everything
around some critical section of code all
the time with actor/model we don't have
those concerns because again the actor
is the the central logical unit of
computation and we have a scheduler that
understands when the actor receives a
message that it must at some point
receive a thread or be given a thread to
run on for some period of time and the
scheduler may allow the actor to run
that single message that it's received
or if there are five messages that have
been in queued for that actor it may
allow it to run all five of those
messages before it takes the thread away
from that actor and decides to give it
to another actor so if you if you look
at the internal
of how an actor/model is is created or
designed you would probably see a thread
pool where the the the pool has a number
of threads that can be optimally used by
the application at any given time let's
say that we have a processor that can
handle up to 16 threads so we've got or
a node a machine that has either a
number of processors or a multi-core
processor and let's just say that the
configuration of this node is such that
it can handle 16 threads at a time
you might decide to have all 16 of those
threads given to this actor/model pool
of threads which would mean that at any
given time there can be up to 16
different actors running on the
processor but it's the task of the
scheduler to schedule each of the actors
in an efficient way that allows that
that processing to take place across
like I said either dozens or hundreds or
thousands tens of thousands even
millions of actors over a period of time
so that the the actions are are complete
and the you know note no actor is
starved for processor ok so what you're
saying I think is that it is the extra
runtime that takes care in this case
akka that takes care of mapping the
application level concept of an actor to
the operating system or runtime level
concept of a thread so as an application
programmer I don't have to do that
myself I can just focus on building
actors which will be mapped to the
underlying resources as efficiently as
the runtime can make it exactly and also
to address I think you you are asking
for sort
the the flavour of programming with
actors it is different it is you know as
soon as you start to deal with
concurrency and you realize I've sent a
message to an actor but the response
that I get back will not cause me to
block until I receive that response but
I could do something else during that
time or I could give up the processor
and allow someone else to use it which
which means I literally do nothing I
just finish the the receive handling of
the message that I've currently received
and I return and when I return the
processor automatically gets or a a
thread on a core gets handed to another
actor to use well that's a different way
of thinking and and as soon as you
realize that you're not doing
synchronous programming anymore and that
you ask an actor a question and you're
not going to block until you get a
response that kind of changes your
mindset and you have to think a bit
differently but it's it's good to learn
to think that way because it allows the
actor model to be as you know performant
as as it possibly can be on a given
machine at any given time with the
number of actors that have to process
messages so what I'm wondering is am I
not exchanging a one way of doing things
for another and just exchanging one
level of complexity for another level of
complexity isn't it the case that at
once I am within the actor world there's
simply a new set of patterns that I have
to learn which are just as good or bad
as the patterns that I'm used to when I
program using the thread model or is
there a you know a difference in the
quality is there a different all those
different kinds of patterns not just
different patterns but really a
different category of patterns that I'm
working with
well there there are a different set of
categories if you've ever use category
of patterns I should say if you've ever
used any sort of messaging middleware
whether it's JMS or MS MQ or or
something like that
rabbitmq whatever it happens to be you
you know that there is a difference
between synchronous and asynchronous
programming so if what if you thought in
terms of sitting down and writing an
application and you would never invoke a
method on another object you would
always send a message and that message
would somehow map to another object and
that object would handle that message
asynchronously and you were going to do
that with JMS or RabbitMQ or ms MQ and
you were going to design an application
that way obviously you're trading one
set of qualities for another and there
are some complexities to thinking in an
asynchronous kind of way and in a
messaging kind of way where everything
is is you know detached from from the
other object and you and you don't have
the actual benefits let's say that we
that we've become spoiled with with
blocking but what I would add to that is
while it is different and while it
introduces a new set of challenges it
also has to introduce a new set of
benefits otherwise we wouldn't use it
and where the benefits are found are you
know let's say for the enterprise that
we're used to working on software that
is you know we get a web request the the
web request comes in it's assigned a
thread at that point in time by let's
say the the thread is assigned by the
web tier and now we have a thread and
now we can delegate internally to our
various layers of software
and we're and we're going to delegate
from a controller to the application
layer and the application layer to the
domain layer and the domain layer will
cause some sort of persistence
interactions and so forth
well what we have to recognize is that
that thread that was assigned from the
beginning is being used 100% by that
single request that came in from the web
and while we're waiting for the database
to do something let's say let's just
pick on the database for a moment while
we're waiting for the database to do
something that thread is blocking and
it's waiting and it might wait for
seconds at a time well we only have a
finite number of threads let's use the
same number I've been using we have a
node that has the ability to run 16
threads simultaneously that means that
that entire powerful machine that that
is running may be blocking 16 different
times on the database and nothing else
is happening on that machine for that
period of time because it can't happen
the we're waiting on the database and we
hat and we we've assigned threads to
requests on the other hand if we think
about actor/model
where instead of blocking for a database
to finish for us we've sent a message to
a database that says we want something
and we know that in some period of time
that database will send a message back
to us that means that we're not blocking
waiting for the database
we're simply inactive and the thread
that would have been assigned to us in a
normal entir web application is now in
use by some other thread that can move
forward so literally we could handle you
know dozens or hundreds of more
application level requests you know from
the web tier then
we could in that same period of time
with just the 16 threads that are end up
going to end up being blocked at the
database instead of being used by other
actors at the same time so that's where
the real payoff comes from and to the
you know the problem that we're facing
with computing is processor speeds clock
speeds have fallen off for about 10
years now I believe if if we were to
look at the trends and so processors are
not getting any faster or not
exponentially faster like we saw in in
previous decades
so as processors are flattening out and
their ability to perform what do we do
if we're if we're still you know only
handling 16 requests at one time the
processor is just sitting there doing
nothing while these these 16 different
web requests are being are blocking for
date some sort of database response
whereas with actor/model we're moving
other things forward with the same
processor simultaneously so that's where
the the payoff really comes about is is
using the processor to the 4 to to the
fully should say so if you were to go to
you know some sort of monitoring if you
could monitor all of the threads or all
of the all of the cores that are running
on a given processor and you were to
look at that emptier web application you
would see you know potentially like a
zero percent if when all of those
processors were we're waiting on
database you you would see a zero
percent usage of of your processors of
your course but with actor/model you
wouldn't see that you would probably
tend to see almost 100 percent
utilization of the processor at all
times even when we are waiting for
database
response to some requests by some actor
to the database well I would argue that
of course you you would configure your
system to use more than 16 threads if
you can run 16 of them you'll maybe use
64 or 128 or whatever the number is
you still absolutely right that what
what most of them will be doing is
probably wait for some i/o operation to
to become become available and so is it
a fair assessment to say the actual
model is a good in-between choice
between the threaded model which is just
described on the one hand and a model
where you just loo use something like
non-blocking i/o asynchronous i/o
explicitly it is it sort of the benefits
of the threat model combined with the
efficiency of the async non-blocking i/o
stuff right right so even even with akka
you may have let's say a database driver
that that is synchronous and so you will
still have something blocking but you
can design your system such that you'll
only have one actor doing all of your
database interactions and in that sense
you're only blocking one thread at a
time and all the other threads are
running you know per the scheduler the
thing that I would say is I've done
enough multi-threaded programming you
know and in real business operations
that I know that I would much prefer to
have used actor model instead of those
multi-threaded you know traditional
multi-threaded approaches like in Java
where I own a thread and I have to make
this thread spin and work just just
perfectly there there are just enough
headaches and and caveats with
multi-threading those typical
multi-threading approaches that if
you're doing anything other than very
trivial kinds of work
I think it's been proven that most
multi-threaded program multi-threaded
code is just absolutely wrong and so at
some point in time even when you think
you've got this multi-threaded solution
working perfectly it's gonna reach up
and bite you in ways that you've never
you know you never planned on and didn't
see coming until it happened in
production and and that kind of problem
will just tend not to happen with actor
model because the model itself is you
know tuned around concurrency and you
really don't have to think about and
worry about the kind of concurrent
problems that would normally happen you
just really are are focused on what this
single actor must do at any given time
mm-hmm so why do you think we have is
this growing interest in the in the
various in the various approaches to
reactive programming why is this now
becoming more more and more important
for people well I think if you look at
the cool kids on the block like you know
some some newer trends and in computing
let's say like Twitter let's say like
Netflix or you know companies like this
that need to profile to find performance
gains in and and really push their
hardware to the very limits at all times
this is where you know companies are
really pushing the envelope and I think
that you know it's it's just simply a
matter of they have to in order to
produce the kind of solutions that they
need to produce for for their
subscribers for their users the the
other side of the coin is though the
enterprise just a typical enterprise
when you think about whether it's
financial organizations or
medical and healthcare organizations or
you know just what whatever you might
think of as being some sort of typical
enterprise software most of these
companies are still riding heavily on
you know the typical j2ee or je kind of
server approach or dotnet or something
like that maybe PHP and because of this
enterprises are are you know if they
want to scale they're either adding
bigger boxes or there or they're trying
to figure out ways to you know scale
their web tier higher and higher but you
know they're they're gonna continue to
sort of reach the point where if they
need to scale beyond what they're you
know they're technical or they're
monetary means are it's going to be very
difficult for them to to scale you know
very easily and I think that that's
where actor/model really needs to make
penetration as into the enterprise where
you know a typical software development
team working on a typical enterprise
application is going to need to use
actor model or reactive extensions more
to make to just basically make better
use of the limited number of computing
resources that they have in the in their
production data centers mm-hmm so one of
the approaches that I know you have
taken is you've sort of implemented or
take taken a look at a bunch of almost
classic enterprise integration patterns
in fact I checked and we had an episode
on a book called enterprise integration
patterns with Lego hoeper in episode 42
of this podcast
almost seven years ago or eight years
ago so how did that experience ago and
how did you how did you arrive at this
idea of doing that right so what
happened is I I was I was working with
actor model some years ago and in fact
with akka and I you know had
conversations with some around the
typesafe that that's the the company
that has developed akka and some of
their trainers and and consultants and
so forth and I was kind of surprised
that akka hadn't yet at the time this is
two-and-a-half years ago probably that
akka hadn't really made inroads into the
into a typical enterprise I was I saw it
immediately as something that you know
should accomplish that so I started you
know just filed that in the back of my
mind and as I was working with actor
model at one point I I noticed some
overlap in the patterns of the
enterprise integration patterns with
Gregor hope and and Bobbie wolf and I I
was just curious to see what would be
actually the mappings if if we were to
take you know all of those patterns how
would they fit into actor model how
could they complement actor model and I
was pleasantly surprised to see that
there's either a one-to-one or near
one-to-one overlap of some patterns with
actor model and also you know where
where actor model doesn't directly
implement some of those patterns that
the other patterns can be used very
extensively in application and
integration kinds of development efforts
maybe you can give us
a brief overview of some of the patterns
that are in that book what is for those
listeners who have never heard of the
book and have never read it what kind of
patterns are in there sure if you looked
at one of the earlier chapters of the
enterprise integration patterns book you
would see patterns like message channel
message pipes and filters various kinds
of messaging routers message translators
and message endpoints so that that's an
early chapter and it kind of takes those
at a high level introduces your you know
the reader to the thought process of how
might I use a message translator or how
might I use a general message router and
then the book fans out from there and
it's it says okay now that you
understand for example what a message
router is what kinds of message routers
are available to you well there are
content-based routers there are process
managers there are different flavors of
message routers so for example akka does
address some kinds of message routers
naturally in its API but it doesn't have
a built-in process manager it doesn't
have built-in let's say splitter or
other kinds of content-based routers
that you might expect it and if you were
to look at messages in general what are
the kinds of messages that you want to
use with actor/model
so there's a generic message but is it a
command type message is it an event
message where you're receiving a
notification of something that has
happened in the past or is it
for example a document message that may
be the result of a query where the the
message carries some notable
cross-section of information but it
doesn't demand that you use it in a
certain way so that's where the hope and
wolf book kind of takes us so you know a
message channel message pipes and
filters message router message
translator and message endpoints
different kinds of endpoints so if you
think of taking each of those sections
and comparing it to akka let's say
message channel well we can compare the
actor model in general or akka to the
message channel pattern that could be
viewed as the FIFO or first in first out
queue associated with each actor or in
other words the actors mailbox where our
message is received and although I think
it's been stated out rightly that there
isn't really a message channel
associated with actor model that is the
closest Association so we can make a
near comparison and and get the benefits
of conceptually comparing an actor and
actors mailbox to a message channel on
the other hand if we look at a pattern
like process manager under message
router well that's a very powerful
pattern that that we can use in you know
very specific ways to design our
application around processes that like
like long-running processes what some
people call sagas this is something that
is very useful when you're using actor
model and akka doesn't provide that out
of the box but it does provide the the
building blocks that we need
to create for example a process manager
so one of the things that we maybe
didn't didn't talk about yet is that
akka is a system that is able to run on
multiple notes not just a single machine
at least that is my that is my
assumption I hope that's yes like one
that is correct so so assuming it does I
have a feeling it kind of blurs the line
between application architecture and
integration architecture and you use the
term your application multiple times
even though the patterns that we talked
about from a book called Enterprise
integration patterns so do you have this
feeling at these that this line is being
blurred or can-can can I can kind of
patterns just be used for both yeah I
it's a good point because originally
when I started on the the process of
blogging about these patterns I sort of
started out more leaning toward the the
integration use of them although
actually the patterns that I was using
was for the application for example
process manager so I think it is blurred
and I think they can be used in both
ways I think if you were to actually
look at various designs that hope and
wolf use it
it was lending itself to integration but
that's because they were writing about
integration and they basically said your
strongest you know method of integration
is to use messaging and therefore
because you're using messaging here are
the patterns that you would use with
messaging well when you look at actor
model it's all about messaging and
you're not you aren't just either
integrating or working in your in your
application model
you're probably doing a bit of both and
process manager is a very very strong
pattern for for use with application
design so let's say that we have a
domain model and we're modeling each of
the concepts in our domain model as an
actor then maybe we need a process
manager that knows how to coordinate the
messages that are being sent between
actors so that we don't couple those
actors too tightly together and they can
you know remain a single responsibility
principle kind of component and so
you'll use a process manager to decouple
those and and track the process
management of it and then just allow the
actors themselves to be focused on what
they do best as a single responsibility
component so I definitely see the lines
blurred I would also say that in using
actor model let's say that you are
integrating with some sort of legacy
system that doesn't support actor model
the other strengths that you have here
is that you can model the integration
using actors but the actors themselves
may just be a set of integration tools
with the legacy system so you're you're
able to model the the problem domain
into a solution that that actually you
know as close to the problem domain and
then behind the scenes you can make the
integration work however it needs to
work so you would have some message
translators you would have some channel
adapters some message bridging going on
there and and so it allows you to keep
your mind focused on the problem domain
and not just so focused on the
solution domain that you forget
conceptually what are we trying to do
here but you can actually model
according to the business concepts
mm-hmm so one of the nice things that I
one of the things that I find nice so
that I consider to be nice about the
actual model is that it actually
actually uses the uses a means that can
be used for cross system communication
and makes it the default as opposed to
solutions to try to make the local
communication model the one that can be
used remotely if you know what I mean is
that's I think a very useful property or
the whole approach so maybe you let me
let me get to that domain aspect anyway
you mentioned in the in the introduction
and I mentioned in the introduction that
you've actually written a book on the
main driven design can you very briefly
define for our listeners what the main
driven design is and also tell us if
there is any connection to the to the
stuff we've been talking about for the
last for the last few minutes sure so
domain driven design fundamentally is
about understanding what is core and
when I say what is core what is
strategically most important to the
business at this point in time we have a
very complex project ahead of us
and we want to make sure that we don't
lose track of what what our focus should
be on the thing that's going to let's
say give us some competitive advantage
or some financial advantage to - you
know with with our business so we're
going to try to focus on what is core
well domain driven design really forces
us to answer the question what is core
and if we have identified our core
concepts those belong in what is called
a bounded context and a bounded context
then continually forces us to say is
this concept core if it is it belongs in
the context if it's not core it's out of
context which means we're going to have
to either implement it someplace else or
buy a piece of software that that helps
us to achieve what we need to have
because it is a necessary thing to
implement this in some way but it's
still not core and so domain driven
design is very heavily driven around
keeping track of what is our main core
strategic advantage for this specific
project and what is not and then
designing software accordingly and it
gives us a set of those kinds of
strategic design tools that help us to
deal with you know what is core what is
not and how do we integrate with other
systems and then also a set of tactical
tools for typically you know how do we
deal with entities in our system how do
we deal with services in our system and
and so forth and it helps us to model
those according to what we call a
ubiquitous language so within a bounded
context is a language that is expressed
in a software model and this software
model adheres to linguistically the
kinds of conversations that we have with
the business about how this software
should work so matute kin and my book
addresses this and also my my workshop
but you know the the thing is that
there's a bit of a learning curve to
grasping domain driven design but you
can also boil it down
to some fairly you know understandable
concepts that you can use keep under
your belt for for project work so given
that we have a set of strategic patterns
and a set of tactical patterns how does
actor model fit in how would we use
actor model like with Scala and akka or
Java and akka or something like that
well I alluded to before what if what if
you actually modeled your domain as a
set of actors one of the tactical
modeling tools that we have in domain
driven design is called aggregate and
the aggregate is basically a
transactional boundary but also a
business boundary in it it tells us
where we should put basically
constraints around a cluster of objects
could just be one object actually it
could just be an entity but it could be
an entity with some other value objects
or other entities and where do we put a
transactional boundary around that such
that we can design our system so that
only one aggregate is committed in a
single transaction at any point in the
business process so that's kind of one
of that's one of the tools is aggregate
well what I find is that an actor model
an actor actually makes a very good
aggregate so like I said before much
earlier an aggregate or an actor forms a
natural kind of transactional boundary
that means that it makes a perfect
aggregate so if we design our domain
model around actors we're automatically
deciding where should our transactional
boundaries be within this system within
this model and
do I want you know what what are the
operations that I want that actor or
aggregate synonymous now to perform and
how do i persist those one of the
projects very interesting project
available with the akka product is the
akka persistence toolkit which really
focuses around what I've been talking
about basically designing actors as
aggregates and using a pattern called
event sourcing to output the
representation of the state of one of
your aggregate actors as a set of events
that are time ordered and if you read
those events back in the same order in
which they occurred originally then we
have the ability to reconstruct the
state of the actor aggregate from
nothing into what its current state
should be according to those events that
have previously occurred so and as as
each message comes in each command
message comes in to an aggregate actor
what it produces as its state transition
is one or more events and those events
get saved in a journal and that journal
is then used to reconstitute the state
of the actor when the actor may go away
for some reason for a period of time
when we need to bring that actor back
into memory and in the system then we
basically reconstitute it from those
saved events the event sourcing is is
that what that technique is called so
yeah I think there's there's a big
overlap I think that with the scholar
language and with akka we have a great
opportunity to cut out a lot of the
boilerplate that exists in the java
language and with
you know some of the ceremony that goes
on there with with programming and just
get down to the ubiquitous language
that's being modeled inside a bounded
context and the just the message
protocol of how you send a message to an
actor Anaka cuts out a lot of the visual
overhead and allows you to just focus on
the ubiquitous language so I think there
there's a lot of really good overlap I
actually reference my book and
domain-driven design fairly thoroughly
throughout the reactive enterprise book
and so I think readers will see a very
good practical overlap there okay so if
if a listeners want to find out more
about this approach about this model
what are some good places to start and
to familiarize oneself with with this
new kind of architecture well right now
my book reactive Enterprise with actor
model is available on safari books
online there's a rough cuts version out
there the book will be in print and in
an electronic form you know in in time
maybe maybe when I listen to that listen
to this podcast we don't know the
schedule yet yeah we know I'd end up
yeah we don't know the schedule yet but
you can certainly see an early
publication of that on Safari books
online and in the first three chapters
of the book I focus on actor model using
actor model as acha and also performance
and how you can see performance gains
with actor model so probably something
like half of the book is just focused
generally speaking on actor model and
then the latter part of the book is an
implementation of 60-plus patterns that
were available in hope and wool
so that's you know that's a good place
to get an introduction to actor model I
would also say that the acha
documentation at akkad IO you can you
can find at least you know your way to
where the documentation is housed there
it's quite good documentation actually
especially at a high level and does you
know provide a fairly good introduction
to it there are some other publications
out there there are a few other akka
books there there's a new book which i
think is very promising it's by one of
its by the lead of the technical lead of
the akka team roland Kuhn and his
co-author is Jamie Allen and that's
called reactive design patterns I
believe that's available in early access
mode from from Manning and Jamie Allen
has another small book on reactive there
are a number of books out there if you
if you just go to amazon.com or
informant calm or something like that
and and look for actor model or reactive
you should find you know probably I'm
gonna say somewhere around four or five
books at this point that are available
so yeah I think that that would be a
good place to start
okay so well it's been a very
interesting conversation
thanks a lot free time yeah it was good
having you on the show thank you very
much Stefan thanks for inviting me it's
been a pleasure
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on twitter at SC
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
you